Guide to the Jasper Alston Atkins Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jasper Alston Atkins papers
1922-1997
MS 1811
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
The papers consist of legal documents, writings, clippings, correspondence, and photographs that document the career of Jasper Alston Atkins. The papers emphasize Atkins' civil rights court cases.
Atkins, Jasper Alston, 1898-1982
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Simona Atkins Allen and Anna Atkins Simkins, 2002-2003.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series and one addition: I. Legal Papers, 1925-1973. II. Personal Papers and Photographs, 1922-1997.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the career of Jasper Alston Atkins, particularly his more notable court cases. The papers consist largely of legal documents and clippings relating to those cases.
The Jasper Alston Atkins Papers were processed as part of a collaborative effort between Manuscripts and Archives and the Yale Law School to document the careers and accomplishments of law school faculty and alumni.
Biographical / Historical
Jasper Alston Atkins was born August 8, 1898, in Winston-Salem, North Carolina. He attended Fisk University in Nashville, Tennessee, and graduated magna cum laude in 1919. He then entered Yale Law School and received an LL.B. degree in 1922. While at Yale, he served as editor of the Yale Law Journal and, upon graduation, was elected to the national honor society, the Order of the Coif.
Atkins started practicing law in 1922 in Muskogee, Oklahoma, with the firm Wesley & Atkins. From 1927 to 1936, he lived in Houston, Texas, and was a partner in the firms Wesley & Atkins and Nabrit, Atkins & Wesley. While in Houston, he also worked as the editor of the Houston Informer and Texas Freeman. Atkins returned to Winston-Salem in 1936 to work for Winston-Salem Teachers College, a school founded by his father. He held the position of executive secretary at the college from 1936 to 1960. He returned to newspaper editing upon retirement from the college, serving as an executive editor for the Freedmen's Publishing Company.
Throughout his career, Jasper Alston Atkins fought for civil rights. In 1935, he appeared before the Supreme Court in the case of Grovey v. Townsend, arguing against a Texas state law that prohibited African-Americans from voting in primary elections. He returned to the Supreme Court in 1959 to argue against the segregation of public golf courses in Wolfe v. State of North Carolina. A suit he filed in 1968, Atkins, Pro Se v. State Board of Education of North Carolina, continuing as Allen v. State Board of Education of North Carolina in 1970, is credited with instigating the discontinuation of the separate but equal policy concerning educational facilities in Winston-Salem and the state of North Carolina.
Jasper Alston Atkins died on June 28, 1982, in Winston-Salem, North Carolina.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
African American lawyers; Civil rights -- United States; Lawyers; Atkins, Jasper Alston, 1898-1982; Yale Law School
- Legal Papers, 1925-1973; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes legal documents, correspondence, and clippings and is arranged alphabetically by case name. The series consists almost entirely of copies of legal documents from cases Atkins was involved in dealing with civil rights.
  - Allen v. State Board of Education of North Carolina, 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 6)
  - Atkins, Pro Se v. State Board of Education of North Carolina, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7 - 9)
  - Grovey v. Townsend, 1926-1943 (Box 1, Folder 10 - 11)
  - Ingram v. Wesley, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 12 - 13)
  - Nixon v. Condon, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Wolfe v. State of North Carolina, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 15 - 19)
  - Wolfe v. State of North Carolina, 1959; 1 (Box 3)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
- Personal Papers and Photographs, 1922-1997; Series II
  Arranged alphabetically, the series includes clippings, correspondence, photographs, and writings. Biographical materials include an application for the American Bar Association's Lawyer Placement Information Service, completed by Atkins in the 1960s, which provides details about his career. The photographs are of Atkins during his time at Yale Law School.
  - Biographical materials, Circa 1962, 1983, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1927, 1956-1960, 1977-1983 (Box 4, Folder 3 - 4)
  - J. Alston Atkins Memorial Lectures, 1986-1997 (Box 4, Folder 5 - 6)
  - Omega Psi Phi fraternity, 1922, 1936, 1953, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, Circa 1922 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Tributes to J. Alston Atkins, 1960, 1981-1985 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Urban renewal in Winston-Salem, NC, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Writings, 1932, undated (Box 4, Folder 11 - 13)
  - Yale University commencement program, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Additional Material, 1957-1985; Accession 2003-M-069
  The addition consists largely of legal materials from Jasper Alston Atkins' cases. A small amount of correspondence and clippings is also included.
  - Atkins, Pro Se v. Scott, Governor of North Carolina etc., et al.
    - Clippings, 1970- 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Legal documents, 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3 - 10)
  - City of Greensboro, et al. v. Simkins, et al., 1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cooke v. State of North Carolina, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Council for Public Interest Law, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - State of North Carolina v. Cooke, et al., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 14 - 15)
  - Wolfe, et al. v. State of North Carolina, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Writings, 1957, 1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)